Rym: It's Tuesday, June 25th, 2024.
Rym: I'm Rym.
Scott: I'm Scott.
Rym: And this is GeekNights.
Rym: Tonight we are talking about bosses in video games.
Scott: Let's do this.
Scott: It's uh, it's warm today.
Rym: It was actually weirdly cold yesterday because it was only 78 degrees.
Scott: Well it was also too windy, so...
Rym: Yeah I didn't actually check the weather.
Rym: I'm pretty sure we were on like the edge of the heat dome or whatever yesterday, so that was why we had this brief slight cooling.
Scott: Yeah I don't know how windy it is now, but I look outside and the trees and the flags are moving, so...
Rym: I mean I just biked home and it was fine.
Rym: It wasn't like yesterday.
Rym: So yesterday, you know, biking home from work like I do, everything's fine.
Rym: And then I go out for a little run.
Rym: And while I'm running, the wind picks up so strongly that debris is being thrown around in the street.
Rym: Like tree branches and garbage and stuff is just flying around.
Rym: I saw a tree branch fly, it didn't like fall down and hit this guy.
Rym: It flew sideways and slammed this guy in the face and kind of fucked him up.
Rym: He was bleeding, he wasn't like hurt enough to go to the hospital, but he was mostly just mad and incredulous.
Scott: Yeah, it's uh, you know, it's like I finally get warm weather.
Scott: It's like, "Wow, we're warm now, hooray, I can go
Scott: outside.".
Scott: It's like, "Aha!
Scott: But we will do what?
Scott: We'll have other things going
Scott: on.".
Scott: Like, "Yeah, we're going to be nice and sunny today, but also random spurts of
Scott: rain.".
Scott: It's like, "Thanks, you're not
Scott: helping.".
Rym: But I had to cut, it was like the wind was strong enough to where it was kind of dangerous.
Rym: I actually went in early.
Rym: I only ran a couple miles, but while I was in the park, before I turned around, there's a softball game going on with kids and the wind picked up again.
Rym: And all the sand in like the softball field rose up into the air in like a tornado-looking solid gun.
Scott: Yeah, well, it's not a professional field.
Scott: No one comes and sprays it with water like at a real baseball game, right?
Rym: And it rises up and all the kids just start screaming and running and the adults are trying to corral them.
Rym: And then they ended up canceling the game and they all went home.
Scott: Yeah, sandlot, that's what happens.
Scott: Should have brought a hose.
Rym: A little bit of news.
Scott: Watering cans.
Rym: Speaking of professional sports, the Stanley Cup is over.
Rym: I learned that this was, according to ESPN...
Scott: It's not over, but it has been awarded, just as it's awarded most years.
Scott: That there aren't lockouts, strikes.
Rym: This was the longest NHL season in terms of calendar days in NHL history, apparently.
Scott: Yep, it was too long.
Scott: It felt like it was the longest and then, yes, it was.
Scott: It was the longest.
Scott: That's why it felt so long.
Rym: I mean, it is almost July and they gave the cup away.
Scott: Awarding the Stanley Cup on June 24th for ice hockey.
Scott: It's like, get out of here with this garbage.
Scott: But the owners want to make more money by having more games.
Scott: It's ridiculous, right?
Scott: It's like you have four, right now at least, they're going to expand, but you have four divisions with eight teams each.
Scott: Perfect symmetry, right?
Rym: Stop that.
Scott: You should have each team play one game away against each non-division opponent and one home game against each non-division opponent.
Scott: And that would get you eight, 16, 24, 48 games, right?
Scott: And then against division opponents, you should go two home and two away.
Scott: So you can't count yourself in your own division.
Scott: So that's seven other teams in your division times.
Scott: four is 28, right?
Scott: So what's 28 plus 48?
Scott: It's 72.
Scott: The regular season should be 72 games, but they don't do it that way.
Scott: They have 82 games.
Scott: So the schedule is 10 games too long and it's asymmetrical.
Scott: And even in your division, you're playing all sorts of weird, like the Rangers only played the Islanders like three times.
Scott: It's like, it's, it's, it's all.
Scott: fucked the fuck up.
Scott: There's some out of division teams.
Scott: you play three times.
Scott: It's like, why?
Scott: It makes no sense.
Scott: It should be 72 games in division four times out of division two times, right?
Scott: That would be perfect.
Scott: You would get this shit done sooner, but they would lose money because there would be 10 less games of, you know, ticket revenues to collect on.
Scott: And hockey is one of the sports that makes a lot of its money from ticket selling.
Scott: So, you know.
Rym: Yup.
Rym: But my news is not that the bad team won the cup instead of the other also bad team, because none of those teams are the Rangers.
Rym: But aside from that, I was rooting for the Oilers.
Scott: They're not, eh, I didn't care.
Rym: You know, both teams had- My only reason was I like watching them play and I like that kind of hockey.
Rym: And I don't super like watching the way Florida plays.
Scott: Like that's- I mean, the only, I guess against Edmonton, I, the thing I have against them is they got shitty players on their team.
Scott: Like Corey Perry and Evander Kane who were like pieces of shit.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: I don't want them to, you know, and then what do I have against Florida?
Scott: It's well, it's Florida, the state.
Scott: It's like, that's, that's already, I agree with you that the way Florida plays is probably very, I respect it from a game, you know, gamesmanship strategy perspective.
Scott: But if I were also, I respect, I also respect their ability to actually execute that strategy, which other team, a lot of other teams say they want to play with that strategy and just don't.
Rym: This is the first time in my life I have seen in a Stanley Cup playoffs game, multiple times, someone on a team just like hold the puck up against the wall and just fucking stand there.
Scott: Yep.
Scott: It's smart.
Rym: In game seven, there was a moment where I didn't see, I don't forget who it was, but someone in Florida crouches down over where the puck is in the corner and he's clearly doing it very carefully because the rule is very specific.
Scott: You can't put close hand over the puck.
Rym: You can't put a closed hand over the puck.
Rym: And if the ref can no longer see the puck, then they're allowed to blow the call, blow the play dead.
Rym: But if the ref can still see the puck, they're not supposed to be able to blow their whistle.
Rym: And he was clearly like crouching to prevent anyone from getting the puck out, but also making sure the ref could still see the puck.
Rym: That is A plus level bullshit that would be removed from a video game in a patch after applauding it once.
Scott: But I agree with you.
Scott: It's not very entertaining or thrilling or right.
Rym: It's the kind of thing you want to design the game to prevent.
Rym: And I was hoping the Oilers would blow through it to prove that.
Rym: nah, you can't really just turtle when you're up by one in the Stanley Cup finals, but apparently you can and it totally works.
Scott: If you're good at it.
Rym: Yeah.
Rym: But no, my news is not that.
Rym: My news is that so there's something called the Khan Smythe Trophy in hockey.
Rym: And it's basically for like what player was the MVP?
Scott: No, that's not what it is.
Scott: It's the it.
Scott: So there was a guy named Khan Smythe who was the owner and GM and coach of the Leafs for a long time.
Scott: And in 1960 something, they made this trophy.
Scott: That's why it's got a big leaf on it and a maple leaf gardens building on it.
Scott: And it's unlike other sports.
Scott: For example, in the NBA, they have a finals MVP, which is the best player in the NBA.
Scott: finals, like not the playoffs, the finals.
Scott: The Khan Smythe Trophy is specifically the best player should be awarded to the best player in the entire playoffs.
Rym: You have the entire season.
Rym: You give it to someone who isn't even in the final round, right?
Scott: You could, they could decide to give it to someone who was eliminated in like round one, but it was just like incredible, but their team lost.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And I get a game seven or whatever.
Scott: Like if someone had a 100 goal game and like game one, they could, and it's decided on by 17 people from the professional hockey writers association and the votes.
Scott: for several years now, I think since 2015, seven, something in the teens of last, last decade, at some point they made the votes public.
Scott: So you can actually see who the people are and how they voted.
Scott: And it's basically a rank choice sort of vote.
Scott: Everyone picks up number one choice and number two choice and number three choice.
Scott: And the 17 people?
Scott: that can't be a tie.
Scott: And that's, that's how that goes.
Scott: Yup.
Scott: And so for, I think the, I think every single time that this has happened, they've always voted for someone who's made it to the finals.
Rym: I don't think someone who got eliminated in like earlier has ever won, but they've only, they rarely like one, two, three, four, five, six times ever have awarded it to someone.
Rym: Now, now I think it's now, I think it's now seven times now, seven times because they awarded it to Connor McDavid on the Edmonton Oilers.
Rym: And you know what I'd say he deserves it.
Scott: Yeah, you could, you can make, you know, it's not hard to make an argument for him.
Scott: He got more, you know, throughout it's, it's an award for the entire playoffs, not the finals.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: And throughout the playoffs, he broke Wayne Gretzky's record for most assists ever in the playoffs as a whole, right?
Scott: Most points or whatever it is.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And it's like that alone is like, you know, and if you look at Florida, the winner, it's like, well, who are you going to pick?
Scott: It's like, you could pick their goalie who was amazing in games one, two, three, but then stunk it up against four or five, six of the finals.
Scott: And in the other rounds was acceptable, right?
Scott: He wasn't blowing the doors off.
Scott: It's not like, you know, like Igor was probably, if you take the whole playoffs better than him.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And then, uh, or even, you know, it's like, yeah, Swamin on, on Boston, right.
Scott: Was probably better than Bobrovsky, but he was eliminated very early.
Rym: So I want to set the stage for all of you on the context for this.
Rym: And then I will tell you what my actual specific news is about this.
Rym: So imagine the Edmonton Oilers have lost three games in a best of seven series.
Rym: They're on their way out the door.
Rym: Their opponent is going to win the cup.
Rym: And then they turn it around and fucking crush them three games in a row, push it to a game seven.
Rym: The game seven is close.
Rym: And in the end they lose.
Rym: And then they are there.
Rym: So then the, the Stanley cup is, is being awarded.
Scott: And you have to do a handshake line first and then, and then you leave.
Rym: Yeah.
Scott: And then the commissioner comes out and gets booed.
Scott: Florida booed him, but not very much.
Rym: They could have booed him more.
Scott: They should have booed much more.
Scott: And then he awards the con Smythe trophy.
Rym: Yup.
Scott: And then they were the Stanley cup afterwards.
Rym: So they award the con Smythe trophy, uh, announcing the name of the first new one, which is Connor McDavid after Connor McDavid has left the ice.
Rym: Having lost the Stanley cup at he's naked in the shower already crying.
Rym: So when they announce it, he doesn't fucking come out to accept it.
Scott: Why would I wouldn't come out?
Scott: Why would you come out?
Scott: I wouldn't come out.
Rym: So even better, I found, uh, on Reddit, a few other photos of, uh, times when the, when the, uh, con Smythe trophy was given to someone who lost.
Scott: It was usually most of the time when a loser wins it.
Scott: It's a, it's a goalie who was so good.
Rym: And the photo of hex doll is great because he's holding the con Smythe and he looks like he gives negative fucks about that.
Scott: No, no one gives a shit about the right.
Scott: It's like, Dave, this is something that I think that hockey has done well, but also as a side effects, right?
Scott: Is that in other sports, it's like, yeah, people care about winning the championship for sure.
Scott: Right.
Scott: But they don't care about the trophy that much.
Scott: It's like the trophy is just like a convenient thing and they make new ones every year.
Scott: that the NHL has been like, our trophy fucking matters is, you know, the Stanley cups, there's Stanley's cup, right?
Scott: There's just one really.
Scott: There's a few couple of them, but it's, it's essentially, there's one, uh, in spirit, there's one.
Scott: And so now no one gives any rat's ass about any of the other awards that you can possibly win in the NHL.
Rym: Let's say I made it to the final round of a playoff of a video game that I was really good at and liked.
Rym: And then I lost in the end and I got basically second place in the entire league.
Rym: I'd be really happy.
Rym: I'd be the, I'd be a third place podium guy meme.
Rym: I'd be ecstatic.
Rym: But hockey players will like, it's the cup or nothing.
Rym: It doesn't matter how deep you get.
Rym: If you don't win the cup, like fuck it.
Rym: They, they, they get.
Scott: so, they're only trying to win one.
Scott: It's like there's only one goes to win that one trophy.
Scott: It's like, if you're not, it's like you get your name written on it.
Scott: It's like you wrote my name on a different trophy.
Scott: Who gives a crap?
Rym: I want my name on the trophy that has pop.
Rym: Pocklington's name X out.
Rym: That's what I want.
Scott: I think his name's fallen off by this point.
Rym: I think, I think it's in one of the rings they've removed.
Scott: I think that ring has been removed.
Rym: So you got any news?
Scott: Uh, do I have news?
Scott: I do.
Rym: Founders of Rivec.
Scott: Oh, right.
Scott: So Richard Garfield, the guy who made magic gathering has been working on this game, uh, called founders of Ravec.
Scott: And basically, you know, he, what he wrote a designer diary that, and I'm all, we can also link to the page where you can pre-order sort of the game.
Scott: Cause it's a GMT P 500, which means they try to get enough orders.
Scott: And once they get enough orders, maybe they'll actually start making it.
Scott: Um, I've already, I've paid for one other P 500 in my life, which is a 18XX game, uh, made by Tom Lehmann, who was the guy who did race to the galaxy.
Scott: You know, it's a new England 18XX game and that game is still not arrived, even though it has enough orders and it's been several years.
Scott: So who knows if, or when this game will arrive, if you order it, it hasn't reached 500 orders as of this podcast recording, but regardless the designer diary is very interesting because Richard Garfield talks about how he make, he learns things.
Scott: And then he makes a game about the thing.
Scott: He just learned to help himself better understand the thing he just learned, which is a super well supported way to learn things very well.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: So he read this book called radical markets, which is a book I've heard of and haven't read by some, you know, economic club and, uh, it's some, it's a boring nonfiction book.
Rym: That's my favorite kind of book.
Scott: But it's, that's a book about, of course, uprooting capitalism and democracy for a just society.
Scott: And one of the ideas in that book is that people who have capital, right, would basically have to always at all times have their capital be up for sale, right?
Scott: You couldn't say I'm not selling my house, right?
Scott: You would have to say my house is always for sale and this is the price of my house, right?
Scott: You'd always have to have a listed price and you, instead of having say, you know, um, you know, auditors or appraisers come and appraise your house, right?
Scott: You would put your own price on your own house.
Scott: This is what it would take me to get out of my house, publish that number.
Scott: And if someone has that number, you have to sell to them.
Scott: And then on top of that, you would say, all right, you're now going to be taxed based on the number you said.
Scott: So if you say a low number, you get a low tax, but someone might just buy your house from you, right?
Scott: If you say a high number, all right, no one's going to buy your house from you, but you might have to pay a high tax now because you have claimed your house to be a high value, right?
Scott: And so Richard Garfield turned this idea into this game.
Scott: founders of Ravec, where there are properties.
Scott: And if you own them, you have to set a price.
Scott: And if another player is going to pay the price, you have to get your property.
Scott: And if you set a high number, you have to pay a high tax.
Scott: And then the taxes, of course, go back into the game to improve the situation for everybody, just like real taxes do.
Scott: And so this is, you know, already just based on that information, it's like, I got to play this game.
Rym: Yep.
Rym: Like I have a potential critique of the economic idea, but that is independent of whether or not it would be fun.
Rym: in the same way that warfare sucks.
Rym: But warfare games can be really fun.
Rym: And evil train baron games are really fun.
Rym: Even if evil train baron should never have been allowed to exist.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: Well, but this is a game where, you know, there's evil going on, but there's been a system putting, you know, you're testing out a system that was put in place to fight that evil.
Scott: But anyway, so it's interesting in the design diary, he says, yeah, every version I tried was interesting, but had major flaws.
Scott: He's like, in some versions, players would have, you know, have an asset that they owned and it would grow in value, but before they could fix the price, someone else would buy it.
Scott: So the value of the asset increased, but the price was still low.
Scott: And the phase of the game where they could increase the price hadn't come yet.
Scott: So someone else bought it from them to a lower price.
Rym: Efficient markets must naturally be real time, or there will be temporal arbitrage, which can be extremely bad for people who are not well informed anyway.
Scott: And the opposite problem also happened, right?
Scott: Is that you would, you know, players would put value, put a high price on something, and then right before tax time, they would lower their price and pay a lower tax, even though they were blocking other people from buying it with their high value that they had set earlier, right?
Scott: Because the taxes also arrive at a certain period.
Rym: You're dancing around the edges of why this is not necessarily a good idea to impose on real markets.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Exactly.
Scott: Well, the other problem is that in a game, you know exactly how much money everyone has.
Scott: There's only like a handful of players.
Scott: So you'd be like, Oh, this asset is worth like a fortune, right?
Scott: I should set a high price, but I see that Rym has $1 and Joey Jojo has $1.
Scott: Why would I ever set the value above $2?
Scott: This is no reason because no, you can't buy it from me.
Rym: So there's no risk to send an incentive to try to make every other player as poor as possible to ensure that I pay the fewest taxes possible.
Rym: And then you get hyper hyper capitalism, right?
Scott: And so this is just examples of, uh, you know, he's recognized these problems and fix them in the game.
Scott: And it actually shows the value of using a game to uncover these problems in, you know, in, if the system implemented in the real world.
Rym: And it's annoying to me that this is not used much in other aspects of government or system design, but you know what entities, you expect government to actually care about doing things effectively.
Rym: Well, there's one area that governments tend to care to do things effectively, and that is fighting war.
Rym: And guess where we have used games for as long as there's been modern warfare?
Rym: war games are like, that's where D and D came from.
Scott: Like the military still does games are war games.
Scott: Yep.
Rym: But imagine if we did the same thing, you made Congress design a game to do healthcare.
Rym: And once the game was good, that's our healthcare system.
Scott: Yep.
Scott: That would be probably a much better healthcare system than what we have.
Rym: I mean, throwing a dart at a wall blind would be a better system than we have, but that's a, that's a second problem.
Scott: But anyway, uh, excited for this game.
Scott: Check it out, order it so that it gets over the 500 and maybe it'll get made in the next five to 10 years.
Rym: Maybe I should put myself on the 500 list.
Scott: Do we don't, do we really need two copies though?
Scott: You do get a very large discount, uh, in exchange for pre-order.
Rym: But anyway, things of the day, I've, uh, Emily and I have been playing through Baldur's Gate.
Rym: We're continuing to play it, uh, multiplayer, which is a very different experience from single-player.
Rym: I highly recommend it.
Rym: Uh, and of course this game is, it is very true to how modern fifth edition Dungeons and Dragons plays.
Rym: So if you like that kind of thing, you'll probably like this game.
Rym: If you don't like how modern D and D plays at the table, you're not going to like Baldur's Gate either because they are very close to each other.
Rym: But this is a cute little, uh, animated or more like an animatic video of the Tom Carty perception check song, but with Baldur's Gate characters and Baldur's Gate situations.
Rym: It's cute.
Rym: It's funny.
Rym: And, uh, things like this happen in that game all the time.
Rym: So what do you got?
Scott: So, you know, I've always been not great at fighting games cause mostly, cause I can't input the inputs well.
Scott: Right.
Rym: Um, but I realized just down, down and left, left, and then you hit a button hard as that.
Scott: Yeah, sure.
Scott: Right.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: Uh, you know, fighting game people are always talking about footsies, like who's got footsies and who don't.
Scott: And they'll yell the word footsies.
Scott: And it's like, you know, I know I sort of understood that footsies was about like maintaining the right distance with the opponent.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And you know, so you can hit them and they can't hit you or whatever, but I didn't really understand.
Scott: There was a game called footsies, which is actually used as to help illustrate, uh, in this short video.
Scott: That is my thing of the day.
Scott: I think I may have made footsies a thing of the day at some point.
Rym: The game did because it's similar to dive kick in that it zooms in on like one very specific aspect of fighting games.
Rym: Yeah.
Scott: I think it might be at least in terms for edge, at least in terms of fighting game education.
Scott: I think footsies is better than dive kick.
Scott: Might not be a more fun game though, but regardless.
Scott: So this person uses the game footsies to illustrate and explain what the sort of rock, paper, scissors of fighting games is.
Scott: And you're watching this video.
Scott: I was like, Oh, that's why I suck at fighting games.
Scott: Cause when I played them, I'm pretty much just going rock, rock, rock, right.
Scott: I never knew about the paper or the scissor.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And so what, what go, if you don't, you know, if you don't watch the video, basically it's like, you got to find a game, right?
Scott: You and your opponent are too far apart.
Scott: You can't, if you punch, you don't hit them.
Scott: So what do you do?
Scott: You walk or dash closer to them.
Scott: And then you're in range and then you hit them.
Scott: Okay.
Scott: Well, what do you do to stop the opponent from walking up to you and punching you in the face?
Scott: You stand still and you use like a long attack, right.
Scott: That sort of covers the space in between you and the opponent.
Scott: So if they get too close, they're going to get hit by your attack.
Scott: Right.
Scott: So now, okay.
Scott: Someone's standing there throwing out the long punch, right.
Scott: Long kick, like, or the crouching, you know, kick.
Scott: it's like, poke you away.
Scott: How do you get in and close to them in order to hit them?
Scott: Well, it's called the whiff punish, right?
Scott: When they miss with that attack that they're using to defend themselves, there's a recovery animation and that's your chance to get in close and hit them.
Scott: Right.
Scott: So that that's the three things.
Scott: And then it's like, well, what do you do if someone's standing there waiting for you to whiff?
Scott: It's like, well, if they're waiting for you to whiff, you walk it up to them and punch them in the face.
Scott: And that's the three things that, you know, and compromise the rock, paper, scissors of footsies in more advanced fighting games, like a street fighter or mortal combat or a king of fighters or, or what have you.
Scott: And that was very helpful.
Scott: And now I feel like I can actually play.
Scott: I'm going to go play the footsies game now that this has been explained.
Rym: It's very interesting to me too, how when you, you know, we just did that panel on distilling games down, like.
Rym: that's something we've thought about a lot.
Rym: And it's, it's always fascinating to me that when you distill down to like the core games, like these kinds of mechanics, they tend to themselves in a vacuum be fun.
Rym: And games that are made of fun mechanics tend to be fun.
Rym: And a lot of games are made of just messes of mechanics that aren't fun.
Scott: But also when it comes to fighting games, I've basically only ever tried to walk up to people and punch them or block, block, block, block, block, and wait for my chance to maybe punch them.
Scott: I've never, I've never whiffed punished or tried to cover attack.
Scott: I didn't know how to do those things.
Rym: I think I just realized something about my own fighting game.
Rym: Cause you know, like I am like really bad at street fighting.
Rym: Like, like somehow you look amazing compared to me.
Rym: Like I am just like preternaturally incapable of playing that fucking game.
Rym: Any street fighter, any version doesn't matter.
Rym: I'm awful.
Rym: But the fighting game that I was pretty good at was the soul calibers that I was decent, not competitive.
Rym: Don't, don't think I'm hubris in here.
Rym: I'm shit, but I would fold my own.
Rym: I'd be pretty good.
Rym: I'd be at our friends reliably, even people who cared a lot about soul caliber.
Rym: But I also realized that I was really good at like boldo.
Rym: And when I think about how I played, if you were describing, try to walk up and hit the guy, I always played with this idea of just try to keep switching up what I'm doing.
Rym: Even if I don't understand necessarily what the game effect of that is.
Scott: Well, I mean, you mean you're a button mashing.
Rym: No, I was thinking like back up, back up, forward, or like do weird attack, weird attack, normal attack.
Rym: Like I'd be thinking in a cycle like that and I'd be deciding like, what are the next two or three things I do?
Rym: But it basically was just rotating through what is effectively things like footsies.
Rym: But I wasn't doing it with any knowledge of how the other person's actions in any way interact with that.
Rym: It was just better than just playing rock all the time.
Rym: It's like I was going rock, scissors, rock, paper, rock, rock, rock, scissors, paper, paper, rock, rock.
Rym: But randomly I wasn't looking at what you were doing.
Scott: But yeah, this video is very short.
Scott: And if you, you know, I think everyone who gives any, even the tiniest crap about a fighting game should, if you don't understand them, cause you're, you know, like me, if you're, if you know more about fighting games, none of this is news to you, but everyone else, this is worth your while to help understand those games.
Rym: All right, let's dive into the main video cause I'm hungry and I got to go vote.
Rym: And I'm playing blades in the dark tonight.
Scott: So I voted early and often, yeah.
Scott: Often you say every time they let me.
Scott: So I missed a vote in New York city.
Scott: It's since like a long time.
Rym: So total aside, uh, we're talking about bosses, like the concept of a boss primarily in video games.
Rym: But, uh, so when I was really young, uh, when video games were new and I started encountering video games and the first time I encountered a video game that effectively had a boss in it, like a Mario one, like there's a boss at the end of it.
Scott: I think it probably was Mario one.
Scott: Yeah.
Rym: Uh, trying to destroy it.
Rym: Well, I'm pretty sure it was Mario one where I encountered this.
Rym: I didn't have an NES yet, but a friend of ours did.
Rym: And we're over at their house and we're playing the games and in world one, four, they said words that messed me up for a couple of years.
Rym: They said, Oh, every four levels, there's an ending guy you have to beat.
Rym: And they called them ending guys and other people.
Scott: I mean, without the communication mechanisms of the present day, you know, my cousins always called like, you know, we would call them levels, but it's like, if you looked at the game, it said world one dash four, right?
Rym: There was a Nintendo world, a Nintendo power article about the definitions of stage board and world in relation to my cousins just said board all the time.
Scott: Even though I said level and other people said world, I didn't hear, I never heard people actually say the word stage.
Scott: Usually stage was referred to as like in a fighting game, choosing the background or something, you know, where it's as opposed to like a level in a Mario game.
Rym: I feel like those terms have lost whatever more specific definitions they had and have morphed over time.
Scott: But you know, kids couldn't communicate with each other.
Scott: So they had regional dialects and no one was telling anyone what to say.
Rym: So I lived in a little cluster of probably about a dozen or two dozen kids who called the ending guy ending guy in all contexts.
Rym: And then I remember we moved to another neighborhood and I was said something, something ending guy.
Rym: And this kid, Kevin, I remember this so specifically because that kid later stole a copy of mega man three from a local bully and sold it to my brother.
Rym: And then the bully came looking for his game and it was all scandal.
Rym: But anyway, I said something, something ending guy.
Rym: and Kevin said, what the fuck is an ending guy?
Rym: What are you talking about?
Scott: And then I mean, you could sort of figure it out what you meant based on the context.
Rym: This kid was a little shit.
Rym: So yeah.
Rym: Well, we're talking about bosses and I think, uh, Mario one, like the Koopas, the bowsers that you fought at the end of Mario.
Rym: Like those are bosses.
Rym: That was the thing that was a, in the early video games, the concept of a boss appeared and became universal, ubiquitous.
Rym: Like even if people don't think about it as a mechanic, like it is well known to almost anyone who plays video games.
Rym: And the concept is even bled into tabletop role-playing games and other types of games as well.
Rym: Even though it's not really in sports, it's not like there aren't bosses in sports.
Rym: Like, ah, you beat the Mets in the game and now you have to go have a fistfight with the shadow Mets.
Scott: That would be awesome though.
Rym: That would be awesome.
Scott: Um, but yeah, I mean, you know, the idea of, of having a boss in a game, right?
Scott: It's like you're playing a game, whatever the loop of that game is, is just sort of rolling, right?
Scott: Following its patterns, increasing in difficulty, decreasing in difficulty, whatever kind of game it is.
Scott: And then it's sort of just sort of, you know, in sort of a narrative aspect, it's like, you want to have some kind of climax, right?
Scott: It's like, you know, no matter how your game is structured, if you don't have this sort of like, you know, big finish, like a finale to your fireworks show, it's sort of like, eh, can you, you know, it's sort of like,
Rym: well, think about precursor games,
Scott: play like a Pac-Man or a Dig Dug.
Scott: It's just like, you just keep playing and playing and playing and playing.
Rym: Let's talk about the first platformer that had an ending, Pitfall.
Rym: Pitfall just goes steadily at the, the amount of fun and interaction you're having is linear the entire time effectively.
Rym: So when you win, it's, that's it.
Rym: There's no boss to fight.
Rym: Nothing happens when you win.
Rym: Right.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: You think about like the earliest game, like a Space Invaders, it's like the, it gets faster and faster and faster and it ramps up the intensity, but there, you, it's like, it's sort of, it's very linear, right?
Scott: Or I don't know if it might be exponential.
Scott: I haven't looked at the numbers for Space Invaders, but either way, right?
Scott: It's just a ramp up, right?
Scott: It's, it's, you know, there isn't this sort of big spike in challenge or divergence, right?
Scott: It's just the same thing the whole time and it can get boring.
Scott: Um, and so a boss is basically just a way to say, all right, we're going to punctuate the action with something bigger, different, exciting, uh, you know, but still the same game and pays almost any kind of game that has, you know, a length to it and is especially a single player game.
Scott: You need something like that at some point, you know, whether it's, whether, you know, most of the time it takes the form of a character that is different from the usual enemies you fight for you to fight, but it doesn't always have to take that form.
Scott: You know, it could take some other form.
Rym: I mean, the, the boss, what, what game designers call the boss today of a level or a stage or a board is, is basically just the climax encounter of that unit of the game that is in some way materially different from everything that led up to that point, but it could still take the same form.
Rym: I take a different form.
Rym: According to Wikipedia, the first video game to feature a boss was a game released for the Plato system in 1975
Scott: called, I've never
Rym: heard of this either, but the game was called D and D and it was basically a bastardized version of Dungeons and Dragons in
Scott: the
Rym: tutor programming language for the Plato system.
Rym: And I'm going to learn more about this after.
Scott: Well, you could say that like D and D campaigns were some of the first games to have, you know, where you didn't have to have bosses, but you typically would structure your campaign about like, okay, here's whatever, a Vecna.
Scott: And it's like, you fight all kinds of other nasties.
Scott: And then at the end of your campaign, you fight the Vecna, right.
Scott: As your, your climax of your story.
Rym: Well, if you go before video games and I'm skimming and while Wikipedia actually says something similar, but it goes very specific, Wikipedia points at Bruce Lee's movies as introducing the concept of bosses, but they specifically cite in the first sentence, his 1971 film, The Big Boss, where he fights a bunch of gang members and then he fights the boss of the gang members.
Rym: That's basically the whole movie.
Scott: Yeah, but it had to be, I mean, there are kung fu movies older than Bruce Lee, and I feel like they all had that same kind of structure where there's, you know, all these other fights.
Scott: And then at the end, you have to fight the strongest guy.
Scott: Maybe that's just the term boss came from there, but they had that structure, the narrative structure of fighting your way to the top and then fighting the biggest guy at the end existed, had to exist before Bruce Lee.
Scott: I can't imagine that was the first one.
Scott: Yeah.
Rym: I mean, well, 1971 is the year of that movie, so I don't know what year.
Rym: different films like that that I like came out without looking them up, but that concept had to be in the 60s.
Rym: Yeah, but that concept is really solid and it's really interesting to me that in the earliest era of video games, like Mario 1 had that very specific structure of every level, you know, one, two, one, three, one, one, one, two, one, three, one, four, and then you would fight a boss that was a bigger monster.
Rym: The screen would stop scrolling and you were just on a screen interacting with this one monster, and this became such an ubiquitous pattern in all game design sense.
Scott: So I think, you know, what made bosses exciting, especially in the early days, but also now, is that sometimes the boss fight is like a different thing than the rest of the game, right?
Scott: Or is played differently and is almost like a sometimes a completely different game than, you know, or at least even if it's the same game, it's still played significantly differently.
Rym: I remember I had a side scrolling component, but then you'd have a boss fight periodically.
Rym: that was a light gun style game instead.
Scott: Yeah, or like in a shmup, right?
Scott: It's like, okay, you're still a ship, you're still shooting upwards, but the boss is, all right, you're not, you don't, instead of having these guys coming at you in waves and whatnot, you're now just shooting this thing at the top of the screen and trying to hit it in its weak spots.
Scott: It's taking up the whole screen.
Scott: It's not going anywhere, and, you know, it's going to blast you with who knows how much stuff that you have to dodge intricately, and it's, that's very different than the other part of the game where guys are coming at you ones and twos at a time, and they die sort of instantly.
Scott: You're not pumping a lot into one spot or trying to figure out which spot to shoot or anything like that.
Scott: You know, it's, you know, it's different, or as in other games, maybe like, um, like, uh, Alfred Chicken, for example, is like a, you know, I just always remember because I love the bosses in that one, even though they're kind of stupid, but it's like you would, the game was a puzzle platformer, but when you got to the boss of the levels, it was sort of like, you know, uh, like a little shmup for your sort of, you know, going around the screen, trying to shoot this guy who's coming after you, and it was nothing like the rest of the game, completely different.
Scott: The other thing that's exciting about the bosses, especially when you're kids with simpler technology, is that just the, the novelty of seeing a thing that is different, right?
Scott: It's like you're, you're playing, you know, Zelda one, and it's like, yeah, every screen just has these little guys that are one square each with different sprites, right?
Scott: And then you go to see a boss and it's this big thing, and it's like these sprites that you don't see anywhere else.
Scott: Someone put together this whole section of the sprite sheet for the game, and you can only see those sprites in this one room.
Scott: It's like, you want to see Ganon?
Scott: He's in this one room.
Scott: That's the only way you can ever see the Ganon.
Scott: And so just like seeing that image when you didn't have pictures of it or an internet to look up sprite sheets, or it's like, you get to see it again.
Rym: And only if you can get to that room and usually take a photo of it with your, they had something like in final, in the final fantasy legend two game.
Rym: I remember, you know, the, the, the monster characters that would eat meat to level up.
Rym: Sometimes you'd fight a boss, like a named story boss, and they drop meat.
Rym: And I got to tell you as a kid without the internet, when a boss drops meat that your character can eat and transform, you expect something good is going to happen when you eat that meat.
Rym: Like, that's really exciting.
Rym: Like, what's my, what's my pet going to do?
Rym: Is it going to turn into a dragon or something?
Rym: Dungeon mashy style?
Rym: But the boss fights, all the bosses tend to, like we've, we've developed this lexicon of talking about bosses in games to the point that a lot of people don't think about where these terms came from.
Rym: Like, I've definitely encountered people who refer to mini bosses and square bosses, but they don't know where mini bosses came from or that square boss is literally from the name square enix.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: Mini bosses.
Scott: I usually associate with mega man and Kirby.
Scott: I mean, mega man is a game that's only about bosses, right?
Scott: Kirby is also about bosses, but less so than mega man, but in Kirby game was a, was a mini boss in dragon, uh, double dragon.
Rym: He'd show up.
Rym: You'd have to fight him.
Rym: He was different from everybody else.
Scott: The beat them ups are also about bosses.
Scott: Um, but mega man, literally the main gate, the stage select screen of mega man is here are the boss.
Rym: Here's the boss.
Rym: Click here to go through his level to fight.
Scott: The game is about fighting bosses and taking their powers.
Scott: That is, you know, it says no more boss game than mega man is.
Scott: Um, but in Kirby, there's a lot of mini bosses.
Scott: It's like, okay, yeah, the boss is wispy woods, right?
Scott: Which is, you know, again, this big thing that's different from all the other levels, right?
Scott: You know, you're fighting a one guy instead of side scrolling, but each level would have like frosty here or the guy with the symbols on his shoulders.
Scott: I forget his name, right?
Scott: We're like, you'd have to stop on this one screen or the big wheel that just drives back and forth.
Scott: It's like, yeah, there's normal enemies all over, but on this screen you have to stop and you can't proceed and see you beat this one guy who's a little bit bigger than all the other normal bad guys.
Scott: Um, and so those are the mini bosses, right?
Scott: They're not the boss of the whole world, but they're still, compared to your normal gameplay, boss-like.
Rym: I would argue mini bosses separate levels into effectively stages.
Scott: Yeah, yeah, you know, but, um, depending on if they let you checkpoint or whatever, who knows how the game is structured.
Rym: The square boss was the concept that I've always loved and I encountered it in Final Fantasy IV.
Rym: Like that was when I recognized that as a thing.
Scott: We called it the square boss because it came from mostly in games created by Square, the company that made Final Fantasy.
Scott: And what they would do is just about every Final Fantasy game, I think literally all of them, possibly, but also many others, you would think you're fighting the final boss of the game, but then, ha ha ha ha ha.
Scott: Actually, there is another boss.
Scott: You thought Zemus knows Zeromas.
Scott: Right, but even Mega Man again, right?
Scott: Mega Man 2, it's like you beat Dr.
Scott: Wily and then another skull, right?
Scott: It's the alien guy, right?
Scott: It's like really just a robot controlled by Dr.
Scott: Wily, but it's still another boss after what you thought was the final, final boss.
Scott: And that's a really great pattern, I think, especially in older games where people don't, didn't know that that was going to happen.
Rym: because like, oh, the first time that happened to me in Mega Man 2 as a kid, that was, that was a fucking situation, right?
Scott: It's like, you think you've beaten the game.
Scott: You're like, yes, yes, I did it.
Scott: This, like, this has to be the end, right?
Scott: I'm at the skull.
Scott: I beat Dr.
Scott: Wily.
Scott: Credits roll.
Scott: Let's go.
Scott: And then it's like, nope.
Scott: It's not over yet.
Rym: Especially because the first time that happened to me, I died immediately.
Rym: I just got crushed.
Rym: Like, I couldn't make it past the first skull.
Rym: The first, like, the final anything.
Rym: I was done.
Rym: Yep.
Scott: Yep.
Scott: Ah.
Scott: So what makes a, what makes a good boss at what makes a shitty boss?
Rym: A boss has got to have some sort of special mechanic and it can't just be random for me.
Rym: Like you gotta, you've gotta be able to, from the game itself, the context, the game provides you figure out the boss's deal by some means other than just trial and error.
Rym: That's, that's one of the main requirements for me.
Scott: I think a boss has to have a deal, right?
Scott: It can't just be, you fight me the same way that you fight all the normal bad guys.
Scott: I just am bigger and I take more hits or whatever.
Rym: Yeah.
Rym: The worst boss in any game is, uh, what's his name?
Rym: Who is not Castro?
Rym: because you're playing as Castro in, uh, Guerrilla War, the NES game that was rebranded in the US to not be about that.
Rym: At the end, the dictator is standing up on a tower after you beat the regular boss and now you have to fight him.
Rym: He just stands there and he has no special deal.
Rym: You just have to shoot him for like five minutes straight before he dies and that's it.
Scott: Yeah, that sucks, right?
Scott: Whereas you look at say, Zelda, right?
Scott: Goma, perfect boss design, right?
Scott: It's like, yes, you have to shoot me in my open eyeball with your arrow, right?
Scott: To kill the Goma spider.
Scott: It's like, it's like you have to use a particular item in a particular way.
Scott: There isn't really any other bad guy that works that way, right?
Rym: And every boss in Zelda is pretty unique, but then you meet Aqua Menace again, but he's just a mini boss when you meet him the second time.
Scott: Well, you know, but Aqua Menace isn't, like, yet, like, he is a little different than a normal guy because he's big and he, you know, his pattern is different, but you can just fight him like a normal guy just standing there.
Rym: True, but it, that works for me because there are so many different bosses in the, in Zelda 1 that every boss has its own deal, so it's okay that one of the bosses' deal is I'm big and I hit you.
Scott: Well, I think all the, I think if you look at later Zelda games, not two, but the ones after that, all the bosses have a deal, right?
Scott: You, especially, like, Link to the Past, you get the, the Helmasaur, it's like, you have to use the hammer to smash his face mask armor off and then you can attack him normally, right?
Scott: You know, or like, there's the, the, the Misery Mire has the eyeball thing, what the hell's its name, I forget.
Rym: Oh god, I hate, I love and hate fighting that thing.
Scott: Yeah, and it's like, yeah, you can't get near it because it's got this pool of poison all around it, you know, it's like, or, you know, that's how you got to make a boss, it has to have something, you know, clever and different to it.
Rym: Well, here is a good example, so Bionic Commando, the original, fantastic game, but the bosses were garbage, just, they were worthless, unfun, no good mechanics, like, nothing going on there.
Rym: Bionic Commando Rearmed replaced those bosses with radically unique, mechanically distinct puzzles to solve, that were effectively bosses.
Rym: Yeah, I don't want to turn this into just a list of all the good bosses we've faced over the years, but I would say actually, Final Fantasy IV had pretty good bosses, in the sense that every boss in that game was also, at least in the Japanese version, kind of a puzzle, that was consistent with the theme of the boss as a character, and had enough visual and textual tells and explanation and context, to where you could figure it out as a player, and it was kind of a puzzle, like, if you just held A and did attack with high levels, that really wouldn't actually beat those bosses, but if you were clever, you could beat him without grinding.
Rym: Animal Well doesn't really have bosses so much, except, I mean, it
Scott: does, it only has bosses, because they got rid of most of the normal things, right, but you're not, you're just not fighting them in a direct sense, right, is, you know, the bosses are just sort of puzzles like everything else, but they're sort of like, you know, the ending rooms of the areas.
Rym: I guess what I really like, too, is when, like, bosses are best when they also, they've got, whatever the music is in your game, no matter how good it is, the bosses have to have better music, the bosses have to have good, special music, that, that's one of the keys to a good boss.
Rym: in a modern game,
Scott: like, yeah, I mean, like we said, about the purpose of the boss is to have this sort of climactic narrative, you know, intense moment, and if you don't emphasize that by changing up the music or, you know, and the, and the scene and all this stuff, it's like, well, you're really falling short of, you know, what you could be doing, right, if the regular music just keeps playing, you know, it's not as impactful, you know, emotionally or anything, so.
Scott: The thing
Rym: I do think is very, very good that many games do, but more so now than they used to, is the trope of, there's a boss that's very hard that you beat earlier in the game, and then way later in the game, that boss appears as a regular-ass enemy, like, all over the place, and then the boss you meet after that is so much bigger or more dangerous than any boss you've encountered, like, that's a good way to escalate the power level of a game in a fun way.
Scott: Also a way to save sprites, you know, you don't, didn't just use it once, use it more times, but also it helps you sort of emphasize the, you know, the epicness, right, of something, you know, where it's like, you know, you have normal bad guys, and then you have boss right after that, you know, and humans are very good at measuring things relatively, and our bodies are literally built that way, like, if you put your hand in some water that's ice cold, and then move it to some lukewarm water, it feels really hot, like you're, like it's burning you, because your body is, senses things relatively, so if you have normal guys next to a regular boss, and then you put normal guys next to the mega boss, the mega boss feels like a regular boss, but if you put normal boss from level one, and then immediately, and then fight the mega boss, it's like, whoa, look how big this is compared to what I thought was big, right, whoa, this is an insane boss.
Rym: ...distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.
Scott: GeekNights is recorded live with no studio, and no audience, but unlike those other late shows, it's actually recorded at night.
Rym: And the Patreon patrons for this particular episode of GeekNights are Alan Joyce, Linky, G-Dread, Willy, Tenebrae, Kacen, Cara Makes Music, Krista Dodd, Christopher Warr, Clinton, Walton, Finn, Joel Hayes, Penny Reimer, Rebecca Dunn, Sam Erikson, Sherwin Ron Harlan, a bunch of people who do not want me to say their names.
Rym: I want to point out that in the final minutes of the Stanley Cup playoffs in Game 7, the turtle strategy was effective, and there's a moment when one of the Panthers players crouches over the fucking puck and sits there, waiting to run out the clock, and the best part is that it worked.
Rym: So tonight, I leave you with...
Scott: Hello out there, we're on the air, it's hockey night tonight.
Scott: Tension grows, the whistle blows, and the puck goes down the ice.
Scott: The goalie jumps and the players bump and the fans all go insane.
Scott: Someone roars, Bobby scores at the good old hockey game.
Scott: Oh, the good old hockey game is the best game you can name.
Scott: And the best game you can name is the good old hockey game.
Scott: Second period, where players dash with skates of flash, the home team trails behind, but they grab the puck and go bursting up, and they're down across the line.
Scott: They storm the crease like bumblebees, they travel like a burning flame.
Scott: We see them slide the puck inside, it's a one-one hockey game.
Scott: Oh, the good old hockey game is the best game you can name.
Scott: And the best game you can name is the good old hockey game.